Tom L Jenkins

PhD

Curriculum Vitae



Profile

An experienced scientist and research professional with a demonstrated history of working on highly diverse projects in both academic and public sector organisations. My areas of expertise include bioinformatics, geospatial analysis, data science and software development. Previous projects include population genomics and whole genome sequencing, predicting habitat suitability using machine learning, and developing software applications for internal and external customers.

Employment

Apr 2022-Present	Bioinformatician & Software Developer	Animal and Plant Health Agency
------------------	---------------------------------------	--------------------------------

Feb 2021-Mar 2022	Senior Data Analyst	Natural England
Dec 2018-Jan 2021	Postdoctoral Research Associate	University of Exeter

Qualifications

2018	PhD	Evolutionary Biology	University of Exeter
2014	MRes	Biodiversity, Informatics and Genomics	Imperial Colleage London
2010	BSc	Marine Biology	Swansea University

Computer Skills

Skill	Bioinformatics, Data wrangling, DataViz, Geocomputation, Modelling, Web development
Tools	R, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Linux, Nextflow, GitHub, AWS, R Shiny, VS Code

Selected Communication and Awards

2022	Interview	Live interview on BBC Radio Wales Drive to discuss published research on coral
		habitat suitability modelling
2021	Interview	Pre-recorded interview on BBC Radio Cornwall to discuss published research on
		red algae population genomics
2019	Award	British Ecological Society Research Grant (£5,000)
2018	Talk	Invited talk at Aquaculture Research Collaborative Hub UK Annual Conference
2018	Award	Heredity Fieldwork Grant (£1,284)

Selected Publications

- ➤ Jenkins TL, Stevens JR (2022). Predicting habitat suitability and range shifts under projected climate change for two octocorals in the north-east Atlantic. PeerJ 10, e13509.
- ➤ Jenkins TL, Guillemin M-L, Simon-Nutbrown C, Burdett HL, Stevens JR, Peña V (2021). Whole genome genotyping reveals discrete genetic diversity in north-east Atlantic maerl beds. Evolutionary Applications 14, 1558–1571.
- ➤ Houston RD, Bean TP, Macqueen DJ, Gundappa MK, Jin YH, **Jenkins TL**, et al. (2020). Harnessing genomics to fast-track genetic improvement in aquaculture. Nature Reviews Genetics 21, 389-409.